<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable addresse to both Houses of Parliament, concerning the succession the fears of popery, and arbitrary government. By a true Protestant and hearty lover of his countrey.</title>
            <author>Halifax, George Savile, Marquis of, 1633-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H320A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215862</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827624</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32047</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44827)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32047)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1849:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable addresse to both Houses of Parliament, concerning the succession the fears of popery, and arbitrary government. By a true Protestant and hearty lover of his countrey.</title>
                  <author>Halifax, George Savile, Marquis of, 1633-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>re-printed, anno Dom. 1681]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A true Protestant and hearty lover of his countrey = George Savile, Marquis of Halifax.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="address">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32047:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Seaſonable Addreſſe To both HOUSES of PARLIAMENT, Concerning the Succeſsion, The fears of Popery, and Arbitrary Government.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>By a true</hi> Proteſtant <hi>and a hearty</hi> Lover <hi>of his Countrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT was the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> practice, before Phyſick was reduc'd into Art or Profeſſion, to carry forth into the Roads and High-wayes, the Diſeas'd, and enquire of all paſſengers concerning the Cauſes and Remedies of their diſtempers; out of whoſe preſcriptions, their Friends ſelected, and applied what they judg'd moſt proper.</p>
            <p>What was then done for the Natural, is now as neceſſary for the Body politick of this Country, ſick almoſt unto death, of <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies;</hi> the plots and devices of the wicked and ambitious; expos'd to all Travellers, among whom good Nature and Self-preſervation have at length, after two years ſilent compaſſion, prevail'd upon me to give my opinion of the Cauſes and Cures of our Evils; which I will offer without fear or favour of Party or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, of Court or City; enquiring how far our apprehenſions of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that have ſo long diſcompos'd us at home, and made us contemptible abroad, are juſt and reaſonable.</p>
            <p>Tho' I confeſs 'tis ſaid, <hi>There never was ſmoak without ſome fire;</hi> yet at firſt ſight it ſeems hard to believe that ſober men ſhou'd ever attempt innovations, ſeldom or never advantageous, always hurtful, becauſe neceſſarily attended with the ſad effects of <hi>Civil War;</hi> a calamity that has ſo lately prov'd fatal to the Kingdom in general, to the Prince and to the Subject. Whence it may be reaſonably preſum'd, when our paſſion is over, and we have fully conſider'd the riſe, progreſs and event of <hi>the Last Rebellion,</hi> we ſhall grow calm and wiſe, permit the King to enjoy his own Prerogatives, and content our ſelves with our juſt Rights and priviledges. 'Twill be time enough (when theſe are invaded, if Religion even then will allow it,) to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or ſtand upon our defence; to offer at it ſooner is madneſs and folly, Rebellion and Impiety.</p>
            <p>For the better coming to our point, 'tis neceſſary we take a review of the times preceding <hi>Forty One,</hi> when from the end of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, the people were, as now, full of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings, repinings and diſtruſts againſt the Government. At laſt the ſmother'd Embers burſt
<pb facs="tcp:32047:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:32047:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:32047:3"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32047:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:32047:4"/>
forth into a Flame; and after ten years Violence, War and Confuſion, and near as many more of Uſurpation and Tyranny, the Commonwealth was ſo far from being better'd, by any of the many changes and expedients, that the recalling our King from his unjuſt Exile was found, and unanimouſly agreed, the only way to prevent its utter Ruine. Our Gracious Sovereign, merciful beyond example, pardons his Rebellious Subjects, the Murderers of his Royal Father, and the Uſurpers of his own Crown and Dignity; loads, even among them, with Offices and Honour, ſuch as ſeem'd penitent, and were capable. He then proceeds, firſt to the reſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> like Vertue ſeated in the middle, and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endanger'd by the two extreams of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Presbytery;</hi> and after, to that of the State in peace and quiet, which we enjoy'd to the envy of our Neighbours. This happineſs occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd a War with <hi>Holland, France</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> to their great Loſs, and the Renown of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> ending in a League of friendſhip and amity, for the general good of <hi>Europe.</hi> Not long after, the King was adviſed to grant a toleration for the eaſe of tender Conſciences, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Traffique and Manufacture. This was preſs'd with arguments, That the want of it occaſion'd <hi>Venner</hi>'s Inſurrection; the Plot in 1662, for which ſeveral ſuffer'd at <hi>Tyburn;</hi> that in 1663. begun in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and carried on in <hi>England,</hi> for which in 1664. divers were exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> as were others after in <hi>London, April</hi> 1666, who confeſs'd at <hi>Tyburn</hi> a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of ſubverting the Government, ſeizing the Tower, and firing of <hi>London</hi> the <hi>September</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing; and withal, declaring there were thoſe behind of their party, that wou'd ſtill effect that deſign, which as to that part was too evident. This is notorious from the hiſtorical ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count publiſh'd in 8<gap reason="math">
                  <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
               </gap>. and confirm'd by the <hi>Gazette;</hi> and therefore I cannot but wonder at the Commons Vote of laſt <hi>January</hi> the <hi>10th.</hi> That it is the opinion of this Houſe, that the City of <hi>London</hi> was burnt in the year 1666 by the papiſts, deſigning thereby to introduce arbitrary Power and Popery into this Kingdom. It wou'd be a great ſatisfaction to the World to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the grounds of this opinion, becauſe that otherwiſe that otherwiſe conſidering they did not purſue it, nor any reaſon aſſign'd what ſhould have hindred, it will hardly gain more credit, than the philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers paradox, that Snow was black. I have read of ſome, who never wanted opinions, cou'd they but find arguments to make them probable, for which their being at a loſs made them ridiculous with the ſober part of mankind.</p>
            <p>The King conſents, and at the ſame time declares a War againſt <hi>Holland,</hi> whoſe inſolence and injuſtice in point of Trade and Honour was become inſupportable. Soon after the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament conveen'd, and apprehending the Indulgence might in time prove deſtructive to the eſtabliſh'd Religion, pray'd it might be revok'd; the King Contrary to the then Miniſters advice, anſwer'd their deſires. Hereupon they grow peeviſh, and thenceforeward vow and ſtudy all the methods of Revenge and Confuſion, tho with the hazard of the publick. Ever ſince we have been continually alarm'd with Libels againſt the Government; at laſt a diſcovery is made of a Popiſh contrivance, ſiſted as far as poſſible by the King in Council, and after ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly recommended to the Parliaments further conſideration. This is purſued, but ſome men laying hold on this, deſign to drive it on to further purpoſes, and under pretence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Kings Perſon and expelling Popery, ſet up Presbytery, and pull down the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy. But there being too ſtrict a bond of mutual love and loyalty between the King and that Parliament, means are now us'd, upon a great Miniſters being impeach'd, to have it diſſolv'd: An Act that anſwer'd not his expectations. A new one is call'd, and exceeding the bounds of prudence and moderation, quickly ſent home. A third is ſummon'd, and the King having to this, as to the former, over and over preſs'd the impartial examination of the Plot, the tryal of the Lords, and the care of the eſtablish'd Religion, wherein by all juſt and lawful wayes he often declar'd he wou'd not follow, but heartily go along with them. But alas! they intended no ſuch thing. The Plot muſt be kept on foot, elſe they wou'd be defeated. The King perceiving they ſtill neglected the good of the publick, breaks them, and ſummonds a fourth at <hi>Oxford;</hi> where I wiſh they may be inſpir'd, with ſoftneſs and prudence, anſwerable to the deſigns of the Place, and the needs of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>After this ſhort account, is it poſſible to believe theſe, who inſinuate, the King himſelf is in the Plot, is a Papiſt, and intends arbitrary Government? Oh<hi>!</hi> ridiculous nonſenſical fancy.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32047:4"/>
If the Plot be againſt his Perſon and Government, and contriv'd by Papiſts, and among them (as <hi>Bedlow</hi> has ſworn) none in <hi>England</hi> but have receiv'd the Sacrament upon't, and he be of the number, he muſt joyn with others to cut his own throat, ſtab, ſhoot, or poyſon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But here's ſome myſtery in this pretty Invention; <hi>Charles Stewart</hi> conſpires againſt the King; this imitating the Long Parliament in his Fathers time, who fought for the King for his politick capacitie, againſt himſelf, his Natural, his Perſon. But if he were a Papiſt, wou'd he have paſſ'd into Laws every Bill tender'd him by both Houſes, as well before, as ſince this Plot, in their disfavour? And yet we know one of the godly party was lately fin'd 500 <hi>l.</hi> for ſaying, The Duke of <hi>York</hi> was a Papiſt, and the King little better; a ſaying no longer minc'd nor whiſper'd, but now loudly and plainly ſpoken every day. Cou'd he have been wrought to change of Religion, in time of his baniſhment, he had not withſtood, the offers of forraign Princes, and the ſolicitations of a fond Mother, to reinſtate him in his own Dominions with abſolute arbitrary power. But he was too much a Chriſtian, and too good a King, not to prefer continuance in exile, to the deſigns of enſlaving his Subjects, either in their ſouls, or in their bodies. Muſt he now, in an Age deſirous of reſt and quiet, be upbraided with ſuch purpoſes, that had reſolv'd againſt them in the heat of his youth, the great ſpur of ambition? Now when to compaſſe this wicked and ridiculous project is as impoſſible, as before it was the contrary; when after his reſtoration, beſides foreign aſſiſtance, offer'd at any rate, and to any purpoſe, he had an obſequious General, a victorious Fleet and Army, and a Parliament, whoſe zeal and devotion ſeem'd in nothing to be bounded but by the limits of his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; when to the immenſe treaſure he was poſſeſt of, beſtow'd among his people with equal bounty as it was given, he might have added vaſtly by the confiſcations of more than half the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Wealth of the Three Kingdoms. But inſtead of this, he often preſſ'd his Parliament to expedit the Act of Oblivion, disbanded his Army, and enlarg'd the Fleet, by making one Squadron of more value than all three in the time of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> diſabl'd, in all his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, without exception, all Papiſts, from bearing any office Civil or Military. Has he not paſſ'd the Bill, excluding for ever all Popiſh Lords out of the Houſe, to which his Father cou'd never be perſwaded? Has he not likewiſe curtayl'd the Royal power by two other Acts, that of the <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and againſt Quartering of Souldiers? Three Statutes, for which he might have had as many Millions, had he inſiſted on a bargain, or known how to diſtinguiſh between his own private Intereſt, and that of the Subject, or the truckling way of Bartring, when the good of his people was concern'd. Why did he, but for the ſake of the Proteſtant Religion. Refuſe the Elder Daughter of the Crown to the Dauphin of <hi>France,</hi> and marry her to the Prince of <hi>Orange?</hi> And this without putting his Parliament to the charge of a Portion, or a much greater Sum, which they would have gladly given, had he made the propoſition. And no other cou'd be the motives of recalling his Troups from <hi>France,</hi> raiſing an Army for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> at the expence of above 200000<hi>l.</hi> more than was given, &amp; his prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Trade with that Crown. Theſe things put a ſtop to the progreſs of that victorious King's Arms occaſion'd his quitting <hi>Meſſina,</hi> &amp; clapping up a general peace, when he was juſt at the point of his propoſ'd Conqueſts. If our Prince intended an arbitrary Government, why, beſides his former neglecting the opportunity, wou'd he diſable himſelf for the future by parting with one of the greateſt inſtruments for that purpoſe, the Court of Wards &amp; Liveries, Tenures <hi>in Capute</hi> and Knight-Service, Purveyance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And what did he receive for this exceſs of bounty for the chiefeſt and moſt uſeful flower of the Crown, but a trifle, a feather, half the Exciſe not above a fourth of the others yearly value. And after all this, Knaves invent, and Fools believe, he is now ſetting up for Tyrrany and Popery, when his years are paſt the heat of ambition, his Coffers empty, <hi>France</hi> diſoblig'd, and his own people alarm'd; and bent againſt it with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable reſolutions of oppoſitions. Can any man imagine, that a perſon, who diſarms himſelf, intends to fight.</p>
            <p>Beſides, What one Illegal Arbitrary Act has he done in his twenty years Reign? Whom has he deſrauded of an Ox or an Aſs, of Leaſe or Poſſesſion? where has he in any one inſtance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> our Rights, Properties or Liberties? What Bill tender'd by Parliament for the ſecurity of our Lives or Fortunes, has he rejected? He paſs'd all without exception. As for the Bill for intruſting the Parliament with the Militia for a limited time, reaſon then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32047:5"/>
and experience ſince, has prov'd it was a needleſs encroachment on the Royal prerogative, without the leaſt proſpect of publick good; and to have parted with that power but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was for ſo long to unking and diveſt himſelf of a power he cou'd not be certain would be ever reſtor'd. As he has freely paſs'd all Laws, has he not as chearfully offer'd to enact any thing that was agreeable to Juſtice and Reaſon for our further ſecurity in Religion, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and property?</p>
            <p>From theſe conſiderations, nothing will appear more vain and idle than our <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> our Factious and Seditious reflections on the Government. I will not ſay without great caution, but we may run into thoſe very things we ſo much dread, and wou'd avoid, <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>French Government,</hi> or (which is equally deſtructive of our Birth-rights and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) <hi>Presbytery</hi> and a <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> This will be no groundleſs ſurmiſe, if we look back, and obſerve that the Leav'n againſt the eſtabliſh'd Conſtitution both in Church and State has ſowr'd almoſt the whole lump; the poyſon of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> formerly known by the name of <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſm,</hi> hatch'd at <hi>Frankford</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> grown to a head in <hi>Scotland</hi> with the Reformation, has infected the generality of the Kingdom, the common Traders &amp; Dwellers in Cities and Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the unthinking and illiterate part of the Gentry, with hatred againſt Monarchy and the Church of <hi>England.</hi> This was certainly the invention of <hi>Rome</hi> to overthrow us, by thus ſowing Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions they wel foreſaw our Kingdom and Church in it ſelf divided cou'd not long ſtand. All the Antimonarchical Principles are the ſame in both, the one as well as the other deny Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the King, the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> will have the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyter Jeſus</hi> his Head. King-killing and Depoſing Doctrine is diſown'd by all honeſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as the Author even of <hi>Plato Redivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus</hi> does confeſs, tho two or three <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have privately aſſerted the opinion as problematical, for which themſelves and writings were cenſur'd and condemn'd as falſe and damnable; But 'tis juſtified, both by Books and Practice of the whole <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party; 'tis ſo plain and freſh in our memories, I need not inſtance in the Authors. St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair is not more Infallible than that of an Aſſembly of <hi>Presbyters</hi> in a National Clasſis or Synod. Men of theſe Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Principles ſtirr'd up the <hi>Late Rebellion,</hi> and being active and diligent, drew in many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary honeſt men beyond the power of retreating. Did not the Faction here tamper in <hi>Scotland,</hi> where the promoters of the Covenant, <hi>that Godly inſtrument,</hi> apply'd to the Crown of <hi>France</hi> for protection, as appears by the Letter found with the Lord <hi>Lowden,</hi> therefore ſent to the Tower?</p>
            <p>But what was the iſſue of this Contrivance, but Confuſion and Miſery through the three Kingdoms, the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party over-power'd by the <hi>Independents,</hi> and theſe again by the <hi>Army;</hi> a Commonwealth ſet up, and ſoon after turn'd into a perfect Tyranny, under <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Cromvel;</hi> after more money had been illegally ſqueez'd from the Subjects, by Ordinances and Loans, Sequeſtrations and Decimations, Exciſe, and other Impoſitions, than was ever known before, or ſince. The people weary, call home their Prince, who by an exceſs of mercy and clemency, ſparing to root up men of theſe Principles, gave way to their infecting others with the ſame humour of diſcontent. 'Tis to be obſerv'd, that the year 1535. is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable for the <hi>Geneva Reformation,</hi> and the ſpawning of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Order, and that our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky home-bred Diviſions were fomented, if not firſt ſet on foot, under hand, by directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Court of <hi>France,</hi> as well as from <hi>Rome,</hi> the Intereſt of that State, as well as of the Church, depending on our Diſtractions; to which end <hi>Richlieu,</hi> that great Miniſter, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd many Penſioners into <hi>Scotland,</hi> as did after his Succeſſor <hi>Mazarine</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> And therefore, there is nothing more inconſiderate than to think we are not now acting, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting <hi>French-Deſigns;</hi> 'tis their buſineſſe to divide us, and yet ſo to manage the Ballance, that they let neither the King nor Parliament have the better, or ever come to a Right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: They can no otherwiſe obtain the Weſtern Empire, and 'tis directly againſt their Intereſt, ever to ſuffer <hi>England</hi> to be either a perfect Monarchy, or an abſolute Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. Thoſe that roar moſt againſt <hi>French</hi> Councils and Meaſures, under-hand-bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains and agreements between both the Kings, know they bely their own Conſcience, and that the <hi>French</hi> have us in the laſt degree of contempt. This the E. of D. printed in his own vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, perhaps not ignorant, that ſome of their Miniſters did, in the year 1677. and 78. before the breaking forth of the Plot, declare, <hi>That Monſieur</hi> L. <hi>had greater Intereſt, and</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32047:5"/>
               <hi>more Friends in</hi> England, <hi>than the D. of</hi> Y. <hi>That the K. had need be on his Guard, for he was in great danger of running the ſame riſque with his Father;</hi> when it was likewiſe enquir'd, <hi>What Intereſt among the People two great Peers had, who have ſince the Plot been the great Pillars of the Proteſtant Religion, tho neither was ever reputed to have any, were Miniſters and Adviſers in</hi> 1670. <hi>and</hi> 71. <hi>very good Friends to</hi> France <hi>and Popery, Enemies to the Triple Alliance, and to</hi> Holland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It was alſo ſaid, <hi>That</hi> 300000 <hi>l. a year beſtow'd in</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> England, <hi>among the Factious and Diſcontented, wou'd better ſerve the Intereſt of</hi> France, <hi>than any Bargain they cou'd drive with the Miniſters.</hi> 'Tis too well known, that the greateſt of theſe two Noblemen made a ſecret journey into <hi>France,</hi> ſome weeks before the <hi>Plot</hi> after ſome private Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here with others, among whom were Sir <hi>E. L.</hi> fam'd for Religion, for Morality, Major <hi>W.</hi> and <hi>H. N.</hi> as notorious for the ſame perfections, and their love of Monarchy, and hatred of a Commonwealth; nor did <hi>A. S.</hi> want his Share in the Conſultation, a ſtout aſſeſſor of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, witneſs'd by his and others living out of this Kingdom, ever ſince the Kings Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, untill they ſaw ſome likelyhood of a change, the one returning about the time the D. of <hi>B.</hi> and the other Lords were in the Tower, and the other a few months before the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of the <hi>Popiſh Conspiracy;</hi> which no ſooner came before the Parliament, than ſome of the great Lords of the Committee for the Examination of the Plot kept their Conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and manag'd much of that affair at <hi>Wallingford-Houſe,</hi> Major <hi>W.</hi> their Secretary, where they concluded to take hold of this opportunity, for the carrying on ſome long-hatched Deſigns of their own. Nor is it to be forgotten, that in <hi>June</hi> before, a Letter was writ by an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſon of the Faction, and can be now produced, <hi>That very ſhortly ſomewhat wou'd be diſcover'd, that wou'd prevent our much longer walking in the dark; and that one of the greateſt Lords ſent to an Aſtrologer to know, whether he was not in a ſhort while to be in the head of</hi> 60000 <hi>men.</hi> The methods agreed upon in <hi>France,</hi> and purſu'd here, were to make a Court and Countrey-party, to ſow and diſperſe <hi>Jealouſies</hi> between both, and widen the Gap with all poſſible Devices; which reſolutions ſome here were the ſooner induc'd to embrace, upon this conſideertion, <hi>That they ſhould not live to ſee the iſſue, and were unconcern'd for what ſhou'd come after.</hi> But yet I am too charitable to think, if we have any <hi>French</hi> Agents at home, they are impoſ'd upon by their own unwarineſs, and the others cunning, to act rather againſt, than with, their knowledge, a part ſo much contrary to the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> and the Duty of a Chriſtian. But however it be, I am morally aſſur'd, we are doing their work; and if we are not Knaves and Penſioners, we are Block-heads or Fools, that are blind and beſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted like men prepar'd for Deſtruction. <hi>Quos</hi> Jupiter <hi>perdere v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lt, hos dementat.</hi> If any one talk thus, he is preſently call'd <hi>a Papiſt and a Tory;</hi> every true Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Loyal Subject, is Branded with Nick-names, and run down by Noiſe and Faction; and he that oppoſes <hi>Popery,</hi> if he defends not <hi>Presbytry,</hi> is but <hi>a Protestant in Maſquerade;</hi> if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and our Legal Conſtitutions, to the diſcredit of a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> he is <hi>a Raſcal, a Villian, and a dangerous perſon,</hi> not conſidering, that we are made Tools and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for <hi>French</hi> purpoſes, betray'd by their Cunning and Adreſſe, to forward and act with our own hands, our Slavery and Ruine. Shall we be ſtill blind and deaf to reaſon and demonſtration? Can we not reflect upon the <hi>French</hi> double-dealing in our late Civil Diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and remember what the Lord Keeper <hi>Puckering</hi> tells the Parliament in Q <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> days, <hi>That the Puritans, even at the time of the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>preparations for Invaſion, were urging and preſſing inteſtine Commotions;</hi> where he largely ſets forth their being as dangerous to the Crown and Mitre as the others, and therefore that both were to be equally ſuppreſſ'd, <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans.</hi> I cannot find, that either have ſince alter'd their Principles, and conſequently cannot but wonder why the Papiſts ſhou'd be perſecuted, and the other countenanc'd, even againſt Law and former Statutes. 'Tis ſurely very imprudent to expect your Houſe will be warm by ſhutting a Window, and ſetting open the Doors. And therefore in this I can free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree with <hi>Plato Redivivus,</hi> that the fear of Popery is not the cauſe of our preſent diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances; I ſhall without regard to Religion, conſider the Papiſts and Preſbyterians as two Factions in the State, like the <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vaſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> party in <hi>Holland;</hi> and as ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounce, that both are to be ſuppreſſ'd, or neither, becauſe by emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing only one of the Scales, the Ballance is broken, and the Court, or Monarchical party is firſt weakn'd and deſtroy'd, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32047:6"/>
after the whole form of Government alter'd into that of a Commonwealth; and I am fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, if that had not been that Authors Deſigns, as to an ordinary Reader is paſt doubt, he he wou'd have ſet down this as one of the Remedies of our preſent Evils. But the contrary was his purpoſe, and in order to it he cunningly, to preſerve the Monarchy, wou'd ſet up a plain <hi>Democracy,</hi> and for an <hi>Engliſh</hi> King, obtrude upon us a <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eg</hi> of <hi>Venice;</hi> for he tells you at large, that the ancient Power of the King is fallen into the hands of the Commons, and therefore to keep up the former illuſtrious ſplendor of the Crown, he wou'd have all its Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els taken out, and ſet about the <hi>Speakers Chair,</hi> the King made a Cypher, and diveſted of all Power but the Name, to keep up the three ſeveral and diſtinct ſhares of the Government, King Lords, and Commons. 'Tis an Ingenious way of arguing, but we are not yet, I hope, ſuch fools to have it paſſe, to venture at play, and not know how to diſtinguiſh falſe Dice.</p>
            <p>Oh! but ſays a <hi>Factious Petitioner,</hi> that takes the Houſe of Commons (ſufficiently prov'd by, the learned Anſwer to <hi>Petyt's</hi> Book, to have had no ſhare in the Legiſlative power) to be the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, all their Votes, how wild and unreaſonable ſoever, as we have lately as well as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſeen in print, to be the ſence of the Nation, and have the force of Laws, and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny any Authority to the Kings Proclamation: This Scribler (ſays he) is Popiſhly affected, a <hi>French</hi> deſigner, a meer Tory; not conſidering, that there is not leſs hazard in ſplitting upon a Rock, than upon a Sand-bank; that if I muſt be a ſlave, and forfeitt my liberty, 'twere at leaſt as good to do ſo under a ſingle perſon, as more; the tyranny of many is much more intolerable than that of one. 'Tis equally deſtructive of my liberty, whether the King or the Houſe of Commons, takes away <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> I am ſtill againſt arbitrary Government, ruling according to pleaſure, not the Laws and known Conſtitutions of the Land, whether aſſum'd by King or Commons; if there be any choice, the odds are againſt the latter; and to ſpeak truth, by what has paſſ'd ſince the Plot, any one in his wits, wou'd believe the King is inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, not an invader; that his frequent Prorogations and Diſſolutions have been his legal defenſive weapons, uſ'd as much for his Subjects ſecuritie, as his own honour; that arbitrary power, is a delicious thing, and therefore aim'd at by our Demagogues and tribunes of the people; bad and to be decry'd, only while in the Soveraign. 'Tis very convenient to cry Whore firſt. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>He that appeareth firſt in his own cauſe, ſeemeth juſt, but his neighbour cometh after and proveth him.</hi> If the people in an Iſland are alarm'd, that an Invaſion is deſign'd, and that only at one Port, and they become ſo fooliſh, as for the guard of that, to neglect and expoſe all other, they do but make the eaſier way for their enemies to land and overcome. Thoſe, who are the Watchmen, the Sentinels of our Safety, ought with <hi>Janus</hi> to have two faces, one behind and the other before, and many eyes like <hi>Argus,</hi> there being otherwiſe no ſecurity againſt ſurprize. I remember in <hi>Thucydide's</hi> that the <hi>Grecians</hi> beſieging a ſtrong City, found no means but Stratagem to become Maſters, which they thus contriv'd: After they had purchaſ'd within ſome Penſioners, they kept the beſieged awake, and put them into great diſtreſs by continual falſe alarms, and, as deſign'd, prepar'd to believe nothing more was intended, than amuſement and diſtraction. The falſe Citizens within taking this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, affirm'd, they ought for the future to make it death to any Watchman to give the Alarm. This decreed, notice was given to the enemie, and without the leaſt reſiſtance, the beſieg'd were taken and undone, when and where they leaſt ſuſpected; whereupon this Proverb was taken up, <hi>Amyclas perdidit ſilentium.</hi> I wiſh we may never run the ſame fate; the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is too eaſie and natural to be dwelt upon.</p>
            <p>And yet I cannot but take notice how the late Houſe of Commons have aſſum'd to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a power extraordinary, and by a Vote without proof or conviction, made eminent men and known Proteſtants, guilty of Popery and <hi>French</hi> deſigns, made them Adviſers and Counſellors according to their own fancies, impriſon'd ſeveral DURING PLEASURE, ſeiz'd Cloſets and Writings without information, and contrary to <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> voted Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, made for the preſervation of the eſtabliſh'd Religion, uſeleſs, and their execution grievious to the Subject, againſt the Proteſtant intereſt, and an incouragement to <hi>Popery, &amp;c.</hi> and among theſe, which is moſt wonderful, a Law made by the darling Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well be ſuppoſ'd to have been a friend to <hi>Popery.</hi> If theſe be not odd and arbitrary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, I know not what they are, nor why that ſhou'd be tolerable or lawful for them,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32047:6"/>
which is not for any, no not for our Soveraign. Conſidering men are afraid the a betters of ſuch practices are not friends to peace and quiet, but rather factious and dangerous, willing to enſlave us to foreign Invaſions, or Domeſtick Encroachments. Whatever may be ſaid to the contrary, theſe actings are but too good grounds for ſuch apprehenſions. The cunningeſt Whores ſeem moſt devout, and inveigh very bitterly againſt the lewdneſs they daily ſtudy and commit. Your rooking Gameſters abhor, if you believe their ſhams and oaths, the uſe of falſe Dice, and the un-Gentleman-like trick of cheating. However, none but Cullies, who want wit or years to make obſervation, can be wheedl'd and drawn in by ſuch pretences.</p>
            <p>Before the diſcovery of the Plot, our Miniſters were reflected on, as deſigning Popery and arbitrary Government, by many ſcandalous Pamphlets, and one in particular call'd, <hi>An Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the growth of Popery,</hi> &amp;c. as if the people were to be prepar'd to believe the whole Court were Popiſh; that while they were alarm'd againſt that party, they might be unprovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to defend themſelves againſt the other. The <hi>Presbyterian</hi> true blue, who, like <hi>Aeſop's</hi> Cat, tho' transform'd into the beautiful ſhapes of our Court-Imployments and Honours, will ſtill be hankering after the old ſport of Mouſing; they will ever be lovers of a Commonwealth, and enemies to Monarchy. This is plain from former, as well as later, proceedings, ſince the diſcovery of the Popiſh Plot, when they began to ſhew themſelves in their proper colours, when they cry'd not only the Court, but the Church was Popiſh, and all that are for the eſtabliſh'd Government. You cannot now be loyal, unleſs you be factious, nor a Proteſtant, if no <hi>Presbyterian.</hi> But pray obſerve, none tell you this, but the ſpawn of thoſe ſeduc'd, or concern'd in the late Rebellion; men turn'd out, or that wou'd get into Court-Imployments, that account themſelves ſlighted or diſoblig'd; men of great Ambition, or of deſperate For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, who make all this noiſe and clutter, to be taken off. To what purpoſe elſe, did the late Houſe of Commons make the Vote againſt the bargain or hopes of Court-preferment, but that ſuch a deſign was driving between ſome leading Members and Courtiers? Can they after ſuch a diſcovery pretend zeal for Religion, and the good of their Countrey? For ſhame, let not Faction and private Intereſt make men forgetful of the publick, of the peace and quiet of the Nation: Let them ſecure our Conſtitutions againſt the encroachments or invaſions of any, whether <hi>Presbyter</hi> or <hi>Papiſt:</hi> and remember that the moſt forward in the <hi>Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> were ſoon turn'd out by others; and becauſe what is <hi>Sawce for a Gooſe, is Sawce for a Gander,</hi> this of courſe will be the fate of thoſe, who now glory in being <hi>Ringleaders of Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to thwart and oppoſe their Sovereign; Nay, it may poſſibly be worſe, the Gentlemen, the Knights of the Shires, may be kick'd out by Mechanicks, by Citizens and Burgeſſes; for he that practiſeth Diſobedience to his Superiours, teacheth it to his Inferiours. Sir <hi>W. I.</hi> Sir <hi>F. W.</hi> Collonel <hi>T.</hi> &amp;c. all know were diſoblidg'd, and if taken into favour, the Employments and Honours they covet, wou'd ſtand up for the Court, as much as now they do againſt it. Whether the Petitioning Lords be not of the ſame temper, will beſt appear from the ſtory of every ſingle perſon. One of them has the humour convey'd with's Bloud. His Father was a Gentleman that appear'd zealous in the long Parliament for the good of his Countrey, the firſt that brought in the complaint of Ship-money. But ſoon after, when he was made a Lord and a Courtier, he chang'd notes, and ſung another ſong, no man more for the Monarchy, in its defence he loſt his life, and at his death publickly repented his actings againſt the Earl of <hi>Strafford.</hi> His Son was made an Earl upon the Kings return, ſent Ambaſſador Abroad, and Lord Lieutenant into <hi>Ireland;</hi> to get this Command, be diſpiſ'd not the Courtſhip and aſſiſtance of Coll. <hi>T.</hi> though a <hi>R. C.</hi> and a Creature of his R. H. to whom he made no ſlender profeſſions; not being ſatisfied with gaining vaſtly in that Station five years, he grew peeviſh in hopes of being ſent the ſecond time, nay, rather than fail, he is content to be Commiſſioner of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, in hopes that by the Courtſhip and Intereſt of ſome Women, no matter what Religion they are of, he may come to be Lord Treaſurer: But not like to gain the White Staffe, and perhaps not caring to govern an empty Exchequer, he bent his thoughts again towards <hi>Ireland;</hi> ſlighting the Treaſury he is outed, and grows more diſcontented; and at laſt turn'd out of Council, the next day he repeats a Speech of E. of S. his making, and unask'd, preſents a piece of Councel and Advice to his Soveraign, pretending as a Peer it was his duty. I am ſorry his zeal made him forget, that Peers have no right of adviſing the King, but when he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32047:7"/>
makes them of his Council, or by Writ Summons 'em to Parliament. And what's very odd, he adviſes juſt the contrary to what he and the other Noble E. had done the year before, when Courtiers. This Noblemans Life wou'd make a Comical Hiſtory; he knows how to put on all ſhapes, and in the late times, was not ignorant how to make an Apple-tree ſupply the place of a Pulpit, he knew how to ſerve himſelf in all turns and changes, and he has not fail'd ſince 1640. to have been often out and in with the ſeveral Higher Powers. To give him his due, he is a man of extraodinary parts, but if one of theſe Lords ſaid true, when he was a Courtier, and the other newly remov'd, they are all fitted and turn'd for confounding and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſing, but not for extricating out of difficulties. He wants not Wit to hold forth in the Houſe, or in the open Air, upon occaſion; nor is he meanly Skill'd in the Methods of Court-Pleaſures, as well as Buſineſs. He muſt have an ill memory that forgets, who adviſ'd the breaking of the Triple-League, and making an Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> and a War with <hi>Holland,</hi> pronouncing in the Language of the Beaſt <hi>Delenda est Carthago,</hi> that a <hi>Dutch</hi> Commonwealth, was too near a Neighbour to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarch; the ſhutting up the Exchequer, the granting Injunctions in the caſe of the Bankers, and laſtly, the ſourſe of all of our preſent misfortunes, the general Indulgence: Theſe things being found of ill conſequence, and the Miniſters remov'd as deſigners of <hi>Popery, Presbytrie, Atheiſm,</hi> or <hi>Irreligion, Arbitrary</hi> or <hi>French</hi> Govermnent; muſt any of ſuch Principles aſſoon as turn'd out of Court, be receiv'd into the Countrey, as if theſe two had different Intereſts? Whoever ſay there is more than one Common-weal in both, are Deluders, and Incendiaries, and Betrayers of the Nation. Thoſe that ſtrive to divide the King and his people, are to be look'd upon as penſioners of <hi>France,</hi> and to be moſt ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd. There are that can tell Tales, what Great man ſince the Plot, offer'd a Reconciliation with the D. and for a Reſtoration to his former Power and Greatneſſe, wou'd be his ſervant to all intents and purpoſes. But the D. cou'd not be perſwaded, one that had as often chang'd Parties, as <hi>Proteus</hi> his ſhapes, and the <hi>Chamaelion</hi> his Colours, cou'd be true to any Intereſt, but his own; and therefore rejected his many Meſſages on this ſubject. Another Peer, whoſe Son is in the Lower Houſe, is the great Tribune of the people, wou'd have had a Dukedom ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the <hi>Garter,</hi> to make both Sing to another Tune. A fourth wou'd fain be a Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor in Reverſion. A fifth not long ſince at any rate of purchaſe, wou'd have been Maſter of the Houſe to the Duke: Strange! that a Proteſtant Lord ſhou'd think of ſerving a ſuppoſ'd Popiſh Prince, and after hope, though thus mounted on Horſeback, to get to Heaven. It wou'd be tedious to give particular accounts of all; only by the way obſerve, that a Young Lord newly come to Age, own'd himſelf to his Majeſtie Diſoblig'd, becauſe after a Voyage to <hi>Tangier,</hi> his great Valour there ſhown, <hi>And ſpending his youth in his Princes Service,</hi> (theſe were his own words to the King) another was preferr'd to the Command of the Lord <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth's</hi> Regiment. I cannot but commend this Noblemans Ingenuitie in owning the true Cauſe, and not pretending, as others, Conſcience and publick good for his motives. But <hi>I</hi> am ſorry he ſhould forget, not only the obligations of gratitude, which he is under, for his Bread and for his Honour, but alſo who ſays, <hi>Appear not wiſe before the King, and give not Counſel unask'd.</hi> He has learning enough to underſtand the meaning of <hi>in conſilium non vocatus ne acceſseris.</hi> 'Tis to be hop'd he may repent, and with more years his wit may be turn'd into wiſdom.</p>
            <p>As for the D. of M. I believe him perfectly drawn in by deſigning Politicians for ends of their own, who never intended him more than as an uſeful Tool, afterwards to be laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. 'Tis no wonder that one of his Youth and Spirit ſhou'd be tempted with the Baits, and Allurements of a Crown, the ſplendor and gaity of Power has blinded many Elder men's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings. But that they never had him in their thoughts, for K. appears from the Author <hi>Plato Redivivus;</hi> and indeed if they had, they went the wrong way to work. They ſhou'd not have engag'd him ſo far, as to deſerve his being turn'd out of his Command as General, a Poſt that wou'd have beſt enabl'd him to ſeize upon, and make good any pretence to the Crown, after the death of his Majeſty. <hi>I</hi> am not apt to believe his Grace is ſorry for what is paſt; <hi>I</hi> am certain it were his Intereſt to throw himſelf at the Kings Feet, and quite the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of thoſe men, who intriguing for themſelves, puff him up with falſe hopes, &amp; yet ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover, that nothing is farther from their hearts than his Exaltation, or what is ſo much in their mouths, publick ſervice to the King and Country. 'Tis much better for him to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32047:7"/>
with the ſecond place in the Kingdom, than by pretending to the firſt, againſt all manner of Reaſon, and the obligations of gratitude, forfeit all, his Fame and Honour, Life and Fortune.</p>
            <p>The Petition being already anſwer'd, I will only obſerve, that His Majeſty, intending to turn them out, ſent <hi>Mr. Secretary</hi> to the E. of E. for a Liſt of the <hi>Papiſt</hi> he mention'd in the Guards; But the <hi>Noble Peer</hi> had none to give, but may be ſuppos'd to have taken the ſtory upon hearſay from ſome, that had the malice to invent it. And now muſt the Nation ſuffer themſelves to be rid by any <hi>Faction,</hi> becauſe deſigning par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular advantages, they guild all with the ſpecious pretences of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reſpect for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by opening her Doors to all Diſſenters, and for the Monarchy, by clipping the Kings power to prevent the Papiſts Contrivances againſt his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Examine whether the zealous ſticklers for the Proteſtant Religion, have any at all; or if they have, whether it be not as far from that Eſtabliſh'd by Law, as Popery? Whether if the King wou'd grant all their deſires, receive them into Offices and Power, they wou'd not ſtand up in juſtification of the Court as fiercely as now they do the contrary? What has been before, may well be expected again. He that conſiders this, and that malice never ſpoke well of any, will give the Factious little credit; eſpecially, when againſt reaſon and ſenſe they wou'd impoſe upon us that the King himſelf is in the <hi>Plot,</hi> or as one of the Members in a print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Speech tells the Houſe, <hi>The Plot is not ſo much in the</hi> Tower, <hi>as in</hi> White-Hall; <hi>there 'tis to be ſearch'd for, and there to be found:</hi> And all this becauſe he will not unking himſelf, and put his Crown into their hands, and againſt Law, his Coronation Oath, and brotherly affection, paſs <hi>the Bill of Excluſion,</hi> to the prejudice of himſelf and the whole Kingdom. This is not a ſingle or private man's opinion, but the judgement of the Supreme Tribunal of <hi>England,</hi> the Houſe of Lords; where upon the firſt reading it was thrown out, with the odds of 63 againſt 31; for which reaſon their Lordſhips are call'd Maſquerading-Proteſtants, Tories, Papiſts, or their adherents; as if the Lords muſt not be allow'd the priviledge the Commons take with any of their Bills, without cenſure and affront. But why for their Act muſt His Majeſty be loyally libell'd and aſpers'd? It had been time enough, one wou'd have thought, to have call'd him Papiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had he rejected the Bill after it had paſs'd both Houſes. Oh! then who cou'd have doubted, but his doing more aginſt the Papiſts than any of his Predeceſſors had been promoting their Intereſt, that this pardoning noman condemn'd, nor ſtopping the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of any Law againſt Recuſants, was making it no Plot, and that paſſing the Teſt was letting in Popery by whole-ſale. He that can believe theſe things, is prepar'd for any thing, to ſay a Lobſter is a Wale, or a Whale a Lobſter; that the Moon is a Green-Cheeſe, and the Sun a round Plate of red hot Iron; and then, I preſume, it may not be decided whether we are Fools or Madmen. Let us not thus idly and unjuſtly bely our Conſciences, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to the Nation and all the World, that nothing can ſecure us againſt Popery, but the ſhaking and alteration of the Monarchy, by the Bill of Excluſion; an Act in it ſelf, unjuſt and impolitick, both for the King and People. No man is to be puniſh'd <hi>ex poſt-facto,</hi> by the Laws of this and all other Countries. Beſides, why ſhou'd the Duke, more then any <hi>Fanatick</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> be outed his Birth-right? The Scripture ſays <hi>You muſt not do evil, that good may come of it;</hi> And prudence will tell us, <hi>That this is an evil, that muſt be attended with greater.</hi> For the minute that it paſſes, the Duke is at liberty to recover his Right by ſecret or open Viol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Force Foreign or Domeſtick; He is declar'd an Enemy and Traitor; condemn'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Tryal or Conviction. This piece of injuſtice muſt be defended by an Aſſociation of an Army; this Army muſt be entruſted in the hands of the King or a General, either may make himſelf Abſolute and Arbitary; and therefore if people are now afraid of ſlavery from the Government, what may then be their apprehenſions? And if they are jealous of the King, what General will they find to entruſt? Thoſe meanly skill'd in ſtory, know that Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Armies have at pleaſure ſubverted Commonwealths and Kingdoms: <hi>Agathocles</hi> from being General, became Tyrant of <hi>Syracuſa; Piſiſtratus</hi> of <hi>Athens, Sforza</hi> of <hi>Millain,</hi> the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dici</hi> of <hi>Florence,</hi> the <hi>Caſars</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and not to go ſo far off, <hi>Cromwel</hi> of the Three Kingdoms. Moſt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors were dethron'd by their Generals; and therefore this cannot but make the King as unwilling as the People, to entruſt this great Power in any perſon. And yet
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32047:8"/>
without ſuch truſt the Act of Excluſion is not worth a ſtraw; nor with it can we be ſecur'd againſt Slavery, whether the Duke conquer or be overcome. The Duke will ſtill find a party, at leaſt if he out-lives the King, in the Three Kingdoms to fight his Quarrel; and if he comes in by force; he may well uſe us as a <hi>conquer'd Nation,</hi> break our old, and give us what Laws and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he pleaſes; Whereas if we attempt no ſuch thing, we ſhall not run the hazard of a CIVIL WAR, the King being as likely to out-live, as to be out-lived by His Brother. If he ſhou'd chance to ſucceed peaceably, he cannot be preſum'd to offer any alteration in Religion ſo much againſt his Intereſt, and who never forwarded any in his own Family, ſuffers his Children to continue in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> knowing that Chriſtianity forbids compulſion for its propagation. To ſay he wou'd be prieſt-ridden, is ridiculous; why he more than the <hi>French</hi> King, who openly oppoſes the Popes Uſurpation, and aſſumes to himſelf the cognizance even of Church-affairs? This is but a pretence to impoſe upon the ignorant and the credulous; if there be not Laws enough already, new ones may be made to prevent any ſuch intention. When all Offices and power are in the hands of Anti-papiſts, I cannot ſee where can be our danger.</p>
            <p>But this, if granted, wou'd not be all, the Monarchy is hereby made elective, and the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor may as well be remov'd, as the ſucceſſor debarr'd. In order to this, is there not a Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Succeſſion publiſh'd, ſhewing that the Monarchy is rather elective than heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary? Of which here I will only ſay, that the Writer is a notorious Plagiary, and ſteals all out of a ſeditious Book writ on the ſame Subject by <hi>Parſons</hi> the Jeſuite, under the Name of <hi>Dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, with deſign of diſtracting the people, and making way for a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Conqueſt and Inquiſition; the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Tranſcriber proves himſelf of the ſame Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical principles, and with equal honeſty purſues the ſame ends, Uſurpation and Slavery. 'Tis not to be doubted, but that there has been frequent interruptions of the Succeſſion of the Crown, but no title, but that of the Sword, was ever put in ballance with proximity of bloud, and he that will oppoſe Fact to Right, is very unjuſt, and argues not upon the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Morality, nor the Laws of Nations. Much ſuch another good Chriſtian, is the Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>The appeal to the City,</hi> who tels us, if we ſet up a King with none or a crack'd title, we ſhall have the better Laws; and inſtances that <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> an Uſurper, a Murderer, and a Tyrant, made excellent Statutes. But he might, had he been juſt, have found the Laws of that King outdone by thoſe of our preſent Soveraign, whoſe title none can queſtion.</p>
            <p>And yet it is not unreaſonable to ſuſpect a deſign on foot of ſubverting the Monarchy, if it be conſider'd, that the paſſing the Bill againſt the Duke, will not alone ſatisfie his adverſaries, who further expect, that all thoſe now firm to the King be remov'd, and their truſt put into conſiding hands; and thus when they had him in their own power, it wou'd be no hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to act their pleaſure. The Speech diſown'd by the proteſtant Lord, and burnt by the Hangman (a fate the Author does certainly deſerve) tells us in plain Engliſh, <hi>We must have a Change, and a King we may truſt, and well affected Counſellors,</hi> with much more treaſonable and ſeditious ſtuff. Theſe things, and the frequent mentioning the fates of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. and <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. cannot but alarm his Majeſty, and reſtrain him from ever complying with ſuch perſons againſt his only Brother. He has ſo often affirm'd the Bill ſhou'd never paſs, that he cannot now without diminution of his own honour, as well as ſafety, alter his well-grounded reſolution, taken upon the ſenſe of conſcience and duty, the preſent and future good of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and people. An act that wou'd be the higheſt violation of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> that ordains none ſhou'd be put by his birthright and inheritance, but by the Law of the Land, and legal proceſs. And therefore I hope, what cannot be ſuppos'd, will be granted, will no longer be inſiſted on, leſt the conſequences prove fatal.</p>
            <p>One thing I cannot but admire, that the Duke ſhou'd be abſolutely excluded on ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of being a papiſt, for otherwiſe he is allow'd by all a Prince of incomparable vertues and endowments, leaving no room for enjoying his right, in caſe he become Proteſtant. Do they ſuppoſe an alteration of opinion impoſſible? that's falſe and fooliſh. There are inſtances of men that have changed often, and to mention no more, the Dukes Grandfather <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. twice alter'd his opinion. Beſides, it is unjuſt, and contrary to their own practice; for L. <hi>Br.</hi> was an impriſon'd Plotter, but as ſoon as he became a Convert, without further proceſs or tryal, he was innocent and acquitted. We do in this exceed the Papiſts in <hi>France,</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32047:8"/>
condemn our Proteſtant Anceſtors, and all others abroad, who accus'd them as Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Rebellious, for oppoſing their lawful King <hi>Hen.</hi> 4: on the ſcore of Religion; for the <hi>Pariſians</hi> lov'd his perſon, and ſtood upon no other condition than his turning Papiſt, to receive him for their Soveraign; as all the other R. C's of that Kingdom had done before. And therefore <hi>I</hi> very much ſuſpect we are grown weary of Monarchy; and with an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy natural to <hi>Iſlanders,</hi> affect a Change tho' for the worſe. To this I am induc'd by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Reaſons, and not a little from a Proteſtant Lords Speech, the laſt Seſſions, <hi>That the people of</hi> Athens <hi>were ſo fond of good King</hi> Codrus, <hi>that they reſolv'd to have none after him.</hi> But to attempt this piece of folly and wickedneſs, will inevitably embroyl us in a Civil War, And of that the event is ſo uncertain, that we ought to dread the loſs of all, by ſtriving to enlarge our preſent liberties. This madneſs ordinary prudence will carefully avoid, becauſe in all probability the King muſt get the better; his condition is not like his Fathers: He has ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Troops, which the other wanted, to Guard his Perſon; he has the Militia in his own hands, he has no <hi>Scotch</hi> nor <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion, to divide or diſtract his Forces; and above all, he has the Parliament in his own power, to let them, Sit or no Sit, at his pleaſure and their good behaviour. And 'tis happy he has this power, to ſecure himſelf from popular jury, at this time eſpecially, when whatever the Papiſts have done, we daily ſee others run into Clubs and Cabals, diſtinguiſhing themſelves by Green Ribbans, by general Committees and Sub-committees, where all Tranſactions of Parliament are firſt deſign'd and hammer'd, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections made, a Common Purſue manag'd, and Agents employ'd in every County, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and influence the people; write and diſperſe falſe News, Libels againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Addreſſes made and ſent into every Shire and Burrough, and if the Members do not go down to their Elections, they can Print for them ſuch Speeches as ſerve their purpoſe. Witneſs one my Lord <hi>Vaughan</hi> ſpoke at his election, though his Lordſhip was not out of <hi>London.</hi> I have not heard before, that Sir <hi>Samuel Morlans</hi> Speaking Trumpet cou'd convey a voice a hundred Miles diſtance. But this is nothing with our <hi>True Protestant Intelligencer,</hi> B. H. who printed an Addreſs from the City of <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> that never was ſeen nor preſented by any of the Inhabitants, as by an Inſtrument under the Town Clarks hand does plainly appear. But though Swearing be, Lying is not, againſt the intereſt or practice of the Godly; the <hi>pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian,</hi> true off-ſpring of the <hi>Ignatian</hi> Fathers, who out do them in the Doctrine of <hi>piae Fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> as well as in all other their immoral and <hi>Antimonarhick</hi> principles.</p>
            <p>And now conſidering that none that have any thing to looſe, can ever get by a Rebellion, and that there is no juſt pretence for one, our Liberties and Properties not being broken or invaded, the Rich, unleſs they are mad, will never begin; and yet with, or without their aſſiſtance, a Riſing of <hi>Jack Cade</hi> or <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> inſtigated by greater perſons, will but inlarge the Regal power, and enrich the Crown<hi>:</hi> And for theſe and many more reaſons, I look upon the Threats or Fears of Rebellion, as idle and vain, as our Jealouſies and Apprehenſions of <hi>Popery,</hi> never poſſible in <hi>England,</hi> but by a Civil War, ſince their numbers here are but as one to 230. and by an exact calculation in the three Kingdoms, the whole number of <hi>Papists</hi> is but as one to 205. <hi>non-Papiſts,</hi> and their wealth and poſſeſſions is not one to 300. If their power had been ſo terrible, they wanted not ſince the Plot, provocations to mak us feel, as well as hear on't. But theſe noiſes are like Armies in diſguiſe at <hi>Knights-bridge,</hi> and Regiments of Horſe hid in Cellars under ground, and blowing up the Thames to drown <hi>London;</hi> artifices formerly us'd to draw in the eaſie and the credulous. But 'tis to be preſum'd, the ſame trick will not paſs twice upon us in one and the ſame Age, while the bleeding wounds of the laſt are ſtill ſo freſh in our memories. To remedy and compoſe our preſent madneſs and diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and prevent future evils, muſt, without doubt be the hearty endeavour of all honeſt men, who expect this will be a healing Parliament, that will make up all our breaches, and unite our diviſions, by the methods of prudence and diſcretion; weighing the true cauſes, and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fit remedles, without regard to faction or intereſt, heat or paſſion; reflecting how unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable it is, to ſuſpect in the King or his Miniſters any deſign of introducing Popery and arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Government; a malicious and idle invention, ſet on foot with purpoſe, to enflame the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by men who were outed, or deſirous of Court-Imployments, diſoblig'd perſons, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32047:9"/>
               <hi>French</hi> Penſioners; That the Bill of Excluſion is not like to paſs, either the Lords Houſe or the King, becauſe in it ſelf unjuſt, impolitick and dangerous, not only to the Prince, but to the Subject: That all other legal ways for preventing Popery and Presbytery, are to be taken by thoſe, who deſign the preſervation of the eſtabliſh'd Monarchy and Religion: That this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, or may with eaſe be ſecur'd againſt the attempts or power of any Popiſh Succeſſor: That our fears in this point are groundleſs, and beſt founded upon accidents, that may never happen: That 'tis the higheſt imprudence to run into real, preſent, to avoid posſible, future evils: That innovations of this ſort wou'd be againſt the Princes intereſt, who having not a <hi>4th.</hi> part of the Revenue, neceſſary for the ſupport of the Crown, muſt be under a necesſity of complying with his people in Parliament; and that his temper, practice and Declarations, ſecure us againſt impoſitions of this nature; That it be conſider'd, whether the unquiet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions from the Plot, may not be laid, by a ſpeedy and impartial tryal and execution of all the accus'd and convicted, and the Kings after granting a general pardon, with ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions as have been uſual. The doing this will beget a right underſtanding between the King and his people, defeat the contrivances of our adverſaries, reſtore us to peace and quiet at home, and reſcue us from contempt and danger abroad, and make the Name of Parliament as famous and renown'd, as ſome Libellers endeavour to make it baſe and odious. How this is to be compaſs'd, you your ſelves are deſervedly made the Judges, and therefore I will not like the fooliſh Orator, teach <hi>Hannibal</hi> the Art of War.<hi>—Fiat Juſtitia, ruat Coelum.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-printed, <hi>Anno</hi> DOM. 1681.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32047:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
